We need a wave of change.
A Plastic Ocean is a documentary film directed by Craig Leeson.
A documentary focused on plastic pollution in the world's oceans.
Himself, played by Craig Leeson.
Herself, played by Tanya Streeter.
The Ocean Cleanup is a nonprofit environmental engineering organization based in the Netherlands that develops and deploys
technology to extract plastic pollution from the oceans and to capture it in rivers before it can reach the ocean.
Their initial focus was on the Pacific Ocean and its garbage patch, and extended to
rivers in countries including Indonesia, Guatemala, and the United States.
The Ocean Cleanup was founded in 2013 by Boyan Slat, a
Dutch inventor who serves as its CEO.
It develops both ocean and river based catch systems.
Its ocean system consists of a funnel shaped floating
barrier which is towed by two ships.
The ocean system is deployed in oceanic gyres to collect marine debris.
The project aims to launch 10 or more approximately 2 km-long (1.2 mi) systems which they predict could
remove 50% of the debris in the Great Pacific Garbage Patch five years from deployment.
The river system consists of a variety of floating barriers and extraction
systems which are anchored within rivers or at rivermouths.
The Ocean Cleanup also publishes scientific papers, and estimates that "1% of worlds rivers
(~1,000 rivers) are responsible for 80% of the pollution in the world's seas".
They aim to deploy their river systems in these 1,000 rivers.
As of January 2026, the organization has removed over 50 million kilograms (50,000
metric tons)
of trash from rivers and the Great Pacific Garbage Patch.